Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
- A bit to the right.
- To the right?
A bit more, keep going.
- Now a bit to the left.
- Left?
- Is that good?
- Yes, that's it.
Only our palace deserves to have this.
It doesn't belong anywhere else.
Amitābha Buddha,
it's okay if His Majesty only writes this once.
It's so hard on my stiff neck!
Peace to Your Highness.
Why did you come in such a hurry?
My Shifu sent me here to bring Your Highness
to the Hall of Mental Cultivation immediately.
What happened?
His Majesty is angry.
Jade, prepare the sedan chair.
Put down the sedan chair.
Your Highness is finally here.
His Majesty was infuriated
and turned all of us out.
Your Highness, please, calm His Majesty down at least.
We will be eternally grateful.
What happened?
It seems to be a memorandum from State Prince Dun.
Do you know what the memorandum was for?
It seems to be asking for a promotion.
"An insatiable snake would try to swallow an elephant."
His son and daughter have just been promoted.
And he wants even more in the blink of an eye.
I agree with Your Highness.
His Majesty could return the memorandum
if he disapproves.
He is never an impetuous person.
Exactly.
How dare you!
Your Highness.
Your Majesty, the tea can relieve the heat in the Liver.
Why don't you ask me what I'm angry about?
When Your Majesty calms down,
you will tell me if you want to.
Take a look at this.
Yun-e is so impudent!
He asks Your Majesty to promote
his mother Consort Dowager Wenxi
to the rank of Noble Consort Dowager
and move her tomb to the prior emperor's Consort Mausoleum.
It is reasonable to grant the prior emperor's
Consort Dowager Wenxi
a posthumous promotion although she died young.
But she didn't have a dignified death.
The prior emperor forbade her to be
buried in the Consort Mausoleum.
If Your Majesty approves,
it will violate the decree of the prior emperor.
How will Your Majesty be able to be at peace?
He obviously wants to set me against my filial piety
and shows no regard to the prestige of
the prior emperor.
And coincidentally,
right after Yun-e submitted his memorandum,
Nian Gengyao proposed that I should
appease the harem
through granting posthumous titles
and restoring the Consort Mausoleum.
So Your Majesty suspects ...
that State Prince Dun is colluding with Nian Gengyao?
Rice-eating ingrates!
Your Majesty, calm your anger.
For the good of your health,
don't be mad because of them.
If this is tolerated, what cannot be?
Even if I would be unfilial to my father
and turn a blind eye to their collusion,
how would this make the Empress Dowager feel?
Also, the title of Noble Consort Dowager
is not appropriate.
The other lords' mothers have not
been granted this title.
How can a forsaken consort be the first to receive it?
If Your Majesty approves, it will create rifts
among both the lords and their mothers.
It will disturb the peace in both the court and the harem.
If I approve,
I will lose support in both the court and the harem.
But if I don't,
they will certainly hold a grudge.
All of our effort to pacify them would have been futile.
Your Majesty has long endured Nian Gengyao.
Will you tolerate him again this time?
Nian Gengyao is allied with many.
Even if I want to remove him,
my chance of success now is merely four out of ten.
Nian Gengyao has been discontent
about me treating Consort Nian coldly.
He has made moves to get closer to Prince Dun,
so he can rely on both the throne,
and its aspirants.
I'm a concubine in the harem
and I would not involve myself in any affairs in court.
I have only read the
"wind, snow, moon, and flowers" with Your Majesty
and have never known that there are moments
when an emperor can feel powerless.
An emperor or an official,
a concubine or a maid,
who can escape the feelings of powerlessness in life?
Everyone's arms are bound by rope.
So for the long term,
Your Majesty has to endure.
I sometimes feel more like a coward than an emperor.
Emperor Jing of Han had to kill Chao Cuo
to quell the Revolt of the Seven Kingdoms.
Emperor Guangwu of Han had to
live with the murder of his brother
in order to revive the Han Dynasty.
To establish stability in his reign,
he had to promote Lady Guo to be his empress
instead of his beloved Yin Lihua.
But after restoring peace, prosperous times followed.
"A man of strong character has the flexibility
to both advance or retreat.”
Your Majesty's tolerance of the temporary aching
will lead to the country's thousand years of thriving.
This is not cowardly, but governing through retreat.
Huan Huan
Your words always bring my mind peace.
I didn't intend them as consolation.
I was simply speaking the truth.
You're right.
I have to endure it.
But what should I do to endure it?
Your Majesty will approve of State Prince Dun's request
granting the title Noble Consort Dowager
to Consort Dowager Wenxi.
Even Concubine Sourire cannot help ...
What should we do, shifu?
How am I supposed to know?
Even Concubine Sourire doesn't.
Your Majesty.
It's all right. Come clean up later.
Your Majesty will
grant the title Noble Consort Dowager
to Consort Dowager Wenxi.
along with an honorary name
and move her tomb into the Consort Mausoleum.
At the same time, promote all concubines
of the prior emperor
and bestow honorary names.
Especially Consort Dowager Shouxi,
who is the head of all consort dowagers.
And crown Her Majesty the Empress Dowager
with the most eminent honorary name
to show Your Majesty's filial piety to
Her Majesty and respect for your brothers.
You’re right. He wants to confer his mother.
Then I’m going to grant all the
consort dowagers honorific titles
in the name of praying for peace for Her Majesty.
So nobody in the court nor harem can disagree.
If so, the civil officials won’t be critical,
and the lords and consort dowagers will also
appreciate Your Majesty’s grace.
But Nobel Prince Guo’s mother
Consort Dowager Serein has become a Taoist nun.
How should Your Majesty treat her case?
Yunli does not care about these kinds of things.
Although Nobel Prince Guo doesn’t care,
I’m afraid some schemers may distort this to
Your Majesty caring less about Nobel Prince Guo.
Your Majesty may as well
bestow the honor upon Nobel Prince Guo.
This won't be difficult.
Since Consort Dowager Serein is a Taoist nun,
an imperial title isn’t proper anymore.
Instead, I’ll regard her as Venerable Abbess Serene.
Now the whole act has been properly arranged.
You deserve the title of My Illuminating Flower.
You notice every detail for me.
Your Majesty attends to everything under Heaven.
I know nothing about governance
so I can only keep an eye on such
trivial matters for Your Majesty.
"A thousand miles of travel is made of single steps."
How could you know that your so-called "trivial matters" are not critical ones?
Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Majesty.
I heard His Majesty was incensed.
So I’m here.
Yes.
But Concubine Souire is already inside with His Majesty.
Please let His Majesty know that I came.
Yes.
Your Majesty, we might as well wait
until His Majesty calms down.
Now that Concubine Souire is with him,
His Majesty doesn't need me.
We will visit the Empress Dowager.
I beg for Your Majesty to extend your favor
and reinstate Consort Nian to Consort Fleur.
If I reinstate her, isn’t it unfair to you?
And how would I quiet down any complaints?
Consort Nian and her brother are alike.
Indulging their pride will slacken their vigilance,
and their mistakes will come to light.
Moreover, only her reinstatement will allow
the Nian family to truly relax.
If Your Majesty can endure for the sake of the country,
so can I endure for Your Majesty.
It will
be an injustice to you.
I don't think it’s injustice.
For Your Majesty,
I’ll do my utmost to tolerate Consort Nian.
All right.
Huan Huan, we lost our child.
I'm deeply sorry.
Trust me.
I will definitely bring you justice.
State Prince Dun wants to confer a title on
Noble Consort Wenxi.
Nian Gengyao seconded his motion.
In the blink of an eye, "dust returns to dust".
No matter how high of a title she receives,
how will she know from "under the Yellow Springs"?
Imperial Mother, do you allow me to confer on her?
Why wouldn’t I allow?
The effort is made for the living.
How can the dead know?
As long as your decision is good for the state,
I accept the impact to my honor.
Thank you, Imperial Mother.
Time has passed and circumstances have changed.
Seeing Consort Nian,
I fear that she will become another Wenxi.
Fortunately, she has no child.
That’s also the reason why I value Concubine Sourire.
She lost her child.
I’ve been feeling guilty about that.
I know your worries.
The musk in Pleasancy, which we exclusively granted
Consort Nian, has already harmed her fertility.
But, unexpectedly, Concubine Souire was affected.
At this point, there is no good dwelling on it.
It’s all right if you are partial towards her.
Just don’t be excessively so.
I’m not a good father.
An emperor makes the decisions
that an emperor has to make.
If Consort Nian had a son,
Nian Gengyao would surely support
this child as the heir to the throne.
Once they would force you to abdicate,
you and I would not even have a place to reside.
But recently, you've made her feel neglected.
Even though State Prince Dun is difficult to deal with,
Nian Gengyao is the knotty one
wielding military power.
Moreover, there has already
been colluding between Nian and Dun.
Therefore,
you need to make the effort to appease Consort Nian.
Not only to comfort her,
but I also have sympathy for her.
After all, she has been with me
for all these years
and treats me with a sincere heart.
I’m an emperor and a father.
When Consort Nian was pregnant,
I had no choice but to kill my own child.
How could it not bring pain?
It was done with Consort Honnête's hands.
Since she has taken all of the blame,
you should let it go.
I have lost so many children.
Who knows whether that is Heaven's punishment.
I personally measured out the herbs
that were sent to Consort Nian.
If someone has to be punished,
it shouldn’t go to you.
In the past, when His Majesty got angry,
I was the one always by his side.
Concubine Sourire is only aiding
His Majesty this one time.
If the Empress Dowager knows,
she will advise His Majesty.
Your Majesty.
Lately, Concubine Sourire has been a regular
visitor to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Concubines are prohibited from
interfering in state affairs.
Concubine Sourire should avoid raising suspicions.
It is not interference
as long as His Majesty permits it.
Not necessarily, Your Majesty.
That is still up to His Majesty's mood.
I agree.
If it pleases His Majesty, he can
discuss matters with her.
If not, she will be considered
as violating the prohibition.
Your Majesty,
His Majesty is heading to the Palace of Earthly Honor.
I knew this would happen ...
sooner or later.
Your Highness!
Your Highness, His Majesty is outside our palace!
Your Highness must get ready.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Are you not happy to see me?
I am, Your Majesty.
I have not visited for some time.
I thought
that Your Majesty would never come to see me.
I was angry with you,
and, I kept myself away from you.
But tomorrow ...
I remember ...
is the day that you were married into the family.
Your Majesty.
Jade, listen.
The snow is melting.
It is, My Lady. You have good hearing.
Spring has come.
All the snow and frost will melt.
My Lady, aren't you troubled that His Majesty
went to the Palace of Earthly Honor?
Until today, I had not known
that even an emperor must compromise on many things.
Since we both have our own concessions to make,
we should be more understanding of each other.
But now that His Majesty is visiting Consort Nian,
she may rise again as a strong enemy, My Lady.
If I confronted an enemy on my own,
I would be helpless;
but if His Majesty and I share one heart,
then my enemies
will also be the enemies of His Majesty.
Your Majesty, please have this tea.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Did you sleep well last night?
Quite well.
I heard the snow melting last night.
It was dripping the whole night.
Your Majesty did not sleep well?
I am only worried that the entire harem
may not have slept well last night.
Her Highness Consort Nian.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
Peace to Your Highness.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Concubine Sourire,
I haven't seen you for a long time.
I feel the same, Your Highness
But I was always thinking about you.
So, even though I haven't seen you for some time,
it was as if I saw you every day.
When I went to see His Majesty yesterday,
Your Majesty was on his mind in the same way.
Do you know everything?
Are you a ringworm in His Majesty's stomach?
I dare not presume so.
Everyone in the harem can see
how much His Majesty misses Your Highness.
I will accept your kind words.
Consort Nian,
His Majesty selected some tributes and
had them sent to your palace this morning.
Do you like them?
I like everthing His Majesty chooses for me.
That's good.
I haven't seen you for so long
that you seem distant from me.
You must come to my palace more often.
I will,
as long as Your Majesty is not bothered.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty comes to my palace every day.
Are you not tired of the meals here?
You have never asked me such questions before.
I'm just worried...
Well, if I leave, you can stop worrying.
Your Majesty!
You are having such foolish notions.
Tell me,
what delicacies have you prepared?
Your Majesty will know when you see them.
Zhen Yuandao bows in respect before Your Majesty.
Zhen Yuandao, please rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
In the court, you are my official.
In the family, you are my father-in-law.
So, don't be bound by formalities.
Su Peisheng, take Mr. Zhen to the seat.
Mr. Zhen, please take a seat.
Thank you, Mr. Su.
Your Majesty summoned me so urgently.
I await your important tidings.
You were promoted to Left-Deputy Imperial Censor
Are you accustomed to your new post?
I thank Your Majesty for bestowing
Heaven's grace upon me.
Please sit.
A family needn't stand and bow to each other.
Concubine Sourire and I are not restrained by
such etiquette when we're together.
Concubine Sourire's temperament
has been indulged since she was very young.
I hope Your Majesty will pardon her
if she has been careless.
I like her personality.
Your Majesty's appreciation is the highest honor
to Her Highness and my family.
I called you here to ask ...
Have you identified trusted candidates for the Censorate?
Your Majesty,
the task has been completed.
In the Censorate,
Right-Deputy Censor Gūwalgiya Emin,
Mr. Xue Congjian,
and Mr. Luo Ping
collaborated with me in secret to gather
evidence of Nian Gengyao's crimes.
But, without Your Majesty's command,
we dared not take any actions.
Since he came back to Beijing,
memorandums to reprimand him have arrived constantly.
I did nothing about them
because I have not formed a proper plan
to strike him down with one maneuver.
I fully understand Your Majesty.
I will render my utmost service to allay Your Majesty's concerns.
I am pleased.
Zhang Tingyu will inform you when the time comes.
I will spare no effort.
One more thing,
since you are in the palace,
would you like to visit Concubine Sourire?
I thank Your Majesty for granting me the opportunity.
Since Her Highness's miscarriage,
my wife and I have worried about her very much.
However, it is inappropriate for an official to enter the harem.
When my wife is granted the honor
to attend to Concubine Sourire,
we will pay respects to Her Highness together.
Don't worry, I will take good care of Concubine Sourire.
Concubine Sourire and I,
we are eternally grateful to Your Majesty.
It's getting late.
I will not keep you for dinner.
Su Peisheng.
Please, see Mr. Zhen out.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Allow me to take my leave.
Your Highness.
What?
We servants and the officials are all happy that
Your Highness restored peace with His Majesty.
As before,
there are still many officials out there
who desire Your Highness's favor.
It's different now.
It was not easy to regain His Majesty's favor.
I must act with more caution.
But His Majesty treats Your Highness the same way as before.
I cannot explain it,
but I can feel that His Majesty treats me differently now.
Although His Majesty has been visiting me frequently,
I have not had my title reinstated.
I cannot put my mind at ease.
As long as His Majesty visits frequently, the reinstatement is just a matter of time.
I heard that the Great General was
again rewarded by His Majesty today.
That's good.
I know my temper is short,
but much better than his.
My biggest worry is that my brother may offend
His Majesty with his boastful manner.
Since he has obtained His Majesty's trust,
I can reside in the harem with ease.
Go and see if the nourishing stew is ready,
and if it is, send it to His Majesty.
Yes.
Your hands are very skilled.
Back at home, I did this for my mother.
You are a filial daughter.
"My body, hair and skin are endowed by my parents."
This is my filial obligation.
I would like to know the reason
that you devote so much time to me.
Your Majesty is His Majesty's mother,
my Imperial Mother,
and a master of the palace.
It is my duty to serve Your Majesty.
I recognize your filial devotion to me,
but you also need to devote more thoughts to His Majesty.
You are so young, but you spend your time here all day.
You have to plan for yourself.
Your Majesty seems doubtful about my intention.
It's not that I wouldn't visit His Majesty.
However,
Your Majesty's good health is His Majesty's wish.
So it's required of me to serve Your Majesty.
Moreover, His Majesty is pleased with
the service of other concubines.
I am unaccustomed to wearing fine adornments.
I know Your Majesty has a keen eye.
Perhaps one day, Your Majesty can
provide me with some advice.
I benefit so much from spending time with Your Majesty.
I hope Your Majesty will not turn me away.
You have a way with words.
With your companionship
and Dr. Wen's attendance,
I will recover my health.
The credit goes to Dr. Wen.
All I have done is follow Your Majesty's commands.
I am not very useful.
I know Your Majesty never uses incense,
but I wonder why not.
Every woman likes sweet scents.
I refrain from using it
to reduce spending by His Majesty's decree.
However,
if I don't allow others in the palace to use incense,
they would complain when they see
Consort Nian using Pleasancy.
Therefore, I would rather forbid only myself from using incense.
Your Majesty is kind and considerate.
His Majesty will appreciate your thought.
It's throwing "a cup of water on a burning carriage".
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
Rise.
By His Majesty's decree,
the palace is informed that Consort Nian
is reinstated to Consort Fleur.
This is His Majesty’s decree.
Yes, you may take your leave.
It's happened.
Your Majesty is not surprised?
It was always expected.
It is like the flowers blooming when spring comes.
But if the flowers are overly dazzling,
they need to be pruned.
Congratulations to Your Highness!
Rise.
It's been such a long wait until today.
Your Highness thought of His Majesty day and night.
Your sincerity was seen.
His Majesty finally relented, and now
highly favors Your Highness again.
I don't really know if that is the case.
Is it really like what you said —
that His Majesty highly favors me again?
That's for sure.
Your Highness sent so many letters to His Majesty.
Even I was moved.
Naturally His Majesty was, as well.
His Majesty wouldn't fail to acknowledge
the sincerity of Your Highness.
Rumors were rampant
so His majesty had to neglect
Your Highness to calm the unrest.
The clouds have dispersed.
Your Majesty can now see the moon.
I don't know why ...
I'm always swayed by gains and losses.
After serving His Majesty all these years,
I can no longer see his heart.
Even if I see nothing else,
anyone can see how fondly His Majesty favors Your Highness.
Put the decree away.
I don't care about the rank of Noble Consort.
As long as His Majesty has me in his heart.
It's this year's new tea.
Meizhuang, please try and see if you like it.
It tastes good.
Thank you for thinking of me.
I rarely see you around His Majesty recently.
So I've been thinking about visiting you.
I feel dizzy in spring and fatigued in autumn.
And I dislike being in a bustling environment.
Meizhuang, I heard that you are favored by the Empress Dowager.
You've been working hard to
serve in the Palace of Longevity.
It's just that Her Majesty doesn't mind my lack of intelligence.
Being in Her Majesty's good graces,
you certainly can reside in peace.
But I...
I haven't been able to eat or sleep well.
Why?
His Majesty treats you fairly in all things.
But it's His Majesty who made the decree
to restore Consort Fleur's title.
When I think about how Consort Fleur
used to "tread upon me",
I can't even fall asleep.
Reinstating Consort Fleur ...
It seems ...
His Majesty has forgotten how painfully
Huan'er lost her child.
It's so bitterly disappointing.
All our previous efforts
have been futile.
My words don't carry much weight before His Majesty.
But you are different, Lingrong.
His Majesty listens to whoever is in his favor.
Meizhuang, are you blaming me?
Lady Vertu, you wronged Lady An.
It's not that Lady An didn't advise against the decree.
Instead, it was Concubine Sourire who
suggested the reinstatement.
You're talking nonsense.
I dare not lie to you, My Lady.
I heard this from Xiao-Xiazi.
Did you mishear it?
Xiao-Xiazi serves His Majesty directly.
He couldn't be misinformed.
Meizhuang, why would Sourire do this?
The gossip spread without any substance.
Huan'er hates Consort Fluer the most.
She wouldn't do this.
But last time,
Sourire also persuaded His Majesty to see Consort Fleur.
Enough.
If Huan'er have something to tell me, she will.
If she didn't tell me, it didn't happen.
Let's not let gossip upset us.
It's time that I should visit Her Majesty.
I won't keep you then.
I shall take my leave.
My Lady,
Lady An was very assertive and knew all the details.
I'm afraid this wasn't "wind from an empty cave ".
I know.
So I have to ask Huan'er first.
If she did persuade His Majesty to restore Consort Fleur,
I will no longer see her as my sister.
But I think she didn't have to go that far.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty.
Rise. I need to talk to you.
I thank Your Majesty.
You may sit.
I haven't spoken with you for a long time.
What have you been busy with recently?
I have nothing that occupies me,
just finding ways to pass the time.
Then tell me
how you spend your time.
I will feel refreshed hearing about it.
The Household Department sent
two cranes to the Imperial Garden.
They look beautiful.
Together with the two sika deers in the garden,
they conceive the scene of
"longevity and long-lasting spring".
The medicine is so bitter.
It numbed my tongue.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, here are some preserved hawthorn fruits.
Sweet-and-sour will calm the Stomach.
They are the best after taking medicine.
You are so filial, as always.
It tastes good.
I‘m glad Your Majesty likes it.
The medicine is extremely bitter.
Your Majesty may feel sick if you eat
something too sweet.
Sweet-and-sour is a more pleasant flavor.
Concubine Sourire,
have you recognized your offense?
Your Majesty, I'm frightened and unaware.
Please enlighten me.
How dare you!
You dared to interfere with state affairs as a concubine.
Your Majesty, she...
I asked her.
Why are you so flustered?
I don't know why Your Majesty said so.
But I would never dare to commit such a heinous crime.
I will allow you to confess.
How much were you involved
in the promotion of the Consort Dowagers?
I believe Your Majesty will make a fair judgment.
I have always remembered that the harem
must not interfere with state affairs.
His Majesty is a wise emperor.
He had already decided to promote the Consort Dowagers.
I could never sway His Majesty's decision.
I was mistaken,
thinking that promoting the
Consort Dowagers was a family matter,
so I dared to say a little.
If affairs of state had been discussed,
I would never dare to interfere at all.
Even if you have no intention of being
involved in state affairs,
you dare to say you have no
self-interest in this matter?
I dare not deceive Your Majesty.
His Majesty, as the head of state,
is always worried about state affairs,
and neglecting to eat and sleep.
I’m fortunate to be able to serve His Majesty.
If I have self-interest,
it is only my hope that His Majesty could live forever in peace
and that I will be taken care of in my peaceful old age.
This self-interest, which concubine in the
harem does not have it?
All right, you may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your self-interest is the same as anyone else's.
Your lives all depend on the Emperor.
As long as the Emperor is here,
all concubines regardless of their status and favor
will still have a life to look forward to.
If the Emperor is gone,
the Empress of course,
will be the distinguished Empress Dowager.
And Lady Cao, for instance,
she at least has a daughter to rely on.
But childless concubines like you and Meizhuang ...
Despite your current glories,
I fear your old age will look bleak.
To put it bluntly,
just waiting for death.
So, the Emperor is the only one
you can rely on right now.
The Emperor told me
that it was your idea to restore Consort Fleur's
status as soon as possible.
Yes.
Was that against your will?
Your Majesty is wise.
Your Majesty is aware that someone is plotting against Heaven.
Though I am dim-witted,
I understand who Your Majesty refers to.
Your Majesty has eyes like mirrors —
in this situation, it is necessary
to calm both the court and the harem.
I cannot interfere with state affairs
for the sake of my personal grievances.
In this matter ...
someone has to bear the injustice.
I would rather that person be me.
Sourire,
I didn't expect you to have such a heart.
No wonder the Emperor is partial to you,
allowing you to accompany him in the Imperial Study.
I'm flattered, Your Majesty.
I do not deserve you saying that.
When the Empress told me that
you were very conscientious
serving the Emperor in the Imperial Study,
I was not at ease.
No concubine is at liberty to enter the Imperial Study.
And you've always been the smart one.
If this cleverness is not used in the right way,
or it blindly leads the Emperor
to handle state affairs or impose punishments according to your personal interests,
you will bring disaster to the nation
and I will not tolerate you.
I dare not, Your Majesty.
Do your utmost in serving the Emperor.
And it will be even better if you can have a child soon.
I thank Your Majesty.
Meizhuang has a calm temperament,
and you have a keen intellect.
After Empress Première passed,
the Emperor did not have any concubines truly to his liking.
If you two can put all your heart into your service,
the Emperor will have no worries in the harem.
Your Majesty flatters me immensely.
It’s time for me to rest,
so you two go and enjoy the day.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Concubine Sourire,
There is an old saying:
"The lack of talent is the virtue in a woman."
I don’t think it makes sense.
But being too talented will lead to a hapless fate.
That would be a shame.
A talented person knows when to advance and withdraw.
They cultivate both blessing and wisdom.
This is really rare.
In this harem, even though you are just a woman,
it is a place where a woman’s tears and smiles
can trigger the changes of "winds and clouds" in the court.
What you say and do ...
Be cautious.
Yes.
Where’s Meizhuang?
She took her maid to the kitchen.
Probably making desserts for Her Majesty.
I'm afraid she won't be available.
Let’s go back.
"Lotuses are harvested south of River Yangtze."
"How endless their verdant canopy expands!"
My Lady.
Speak.
This afternoon,
I saw Lady Vertu coming out of the
Palace of Longevity in anger.
Concubine Sourire also came out soon after.
I wonder if Lady Vertu offended the Empress Dowager.
How could she be angry if
she offended the Empress Dowager?
What made her so angry was her knowing that
it was Concubine Sourire who made
His Majesty reinstate Consort Fleur.
When you told her that the other day,
she refused to believe you, My Lady.
She was not entirely unconvinced.
She harbored suspicion and it was confirmed.
That is why she was incensed.
I would very much like to see
whether someone who treats Concubine Sourire like a sister
will never doubt her sister
and never develop a rift.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.